<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peoples plea: fully vindicating the povver and proceedings of the Parliament. Occasioned by a defence of the covenant. /</title>
            <author>Robinson, John, prebendary of Westminster.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91892</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E328_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861347</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861347</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113480</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91892)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113480)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E328[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peoples plea: fully vindicating the povver and proceedings of the Parliament. Occasioned by a defence of the covenant. /</title>
                  <author>Robinson, John, prebendary of Westminster.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Bostock, at the Kings Head in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reverend divine = John Robinson, prebendary of Westminster.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "By Dr Robinson prebend of Westminster formerly a great malignant"; "March: 13 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643). --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:113480:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed according to Order, by <hi>Thomas Paine,</hi> for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illiam Ley,</hi> at <hi>Paules-Chaine,</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113480:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Peoples Plea: Fully vindicating The POVVER and PROCEEDINGS OF THE PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned by a defence of the COVENANT.</p>
            <p>Written by a reverend Divine.</p>
            <q>
               <l>That Rule is eternall,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Salus Populi ſuprema Lex:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Peoples ſafety is the higheſt Law.</l>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Joſ. Nor. <hi>The Peace-maker.</hi> Sect. 22.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for ROBERT BOSTOCK, at the Kings Head in PAULS Church-yard. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113480:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113480:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et me deſire thee not to miſtake. This ſmall Tract was not written ſo much out of deſire to perſwade one Miniſter, as out of hope that ſuch motives wherewith my ſelfe was ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, may prevaile with others alſo, rationall men, which are ſo doubtfull. I know it will appear but as a little Skeleton, a few ſinews and bones, without that filling of fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ornaments of learning, which a better accommodation for books might have afforded: Not many (perhaps) of my calling have been more verſt in this argument, or more averſe from popularitie than I have been. But I have ever held my courſe according as mine owne intereſt did ſeeme to lead me with the tide of that time; nor did I want reaſons out of <hi>Barkley, Blackwood, Bodine, Hayward,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and others, to work mee into a beleefe of ſome truth in thoſe opinions. For <hi>Facilè credimus, quod volumus.</hi> Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally two Achillean arguments, as they appeared then, the one from a Kings Supremacie, which in a true Monarchy did ſeem unqueſtionable, much more in ſuch a Monarchy, where it was ſworne to. The other argument from a Kings immediate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance upon God: But in theſe great differences of the State, ſeeing ſo many wiſe and religious men of a different beleefe, and being reſolved to ſacrifice to the Publike, all mine owne poore pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſt in Church-preferments; I took off my ſelfe a while from thoſe pre-conceptions, and freely examined all from the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie originall and ground-work of all government, and compared it with the practice of our own State; where I found things much differing from what I did imagine before. For indeed neither I, nor many others, did ever truly underſtand the nature of an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh
<pb facs="tcp:113480:3"/>
Parliament before. It is verie true, the King is ſupreme, and we do ſweare it in theſe two reſpect: Firſt, in the ordinarie adminiſtration of the Government, and execution of the Lawes and Cuſtomes of the Realme, hee is the Supreme, the Primuin Mobile, the firſt Wheele that ſets all the reſt a going. Secondly, in relation to all other forraine Princes and States (eſpecially the Pope) he is ſupreme, Independent, holding from none, nor owing ſubjection or fealtie to any, and this is the ground of our oath. The Duke of Normandy heretofore, and other free Princes of France, were ſupreme in their owne Dominions in the former ſenſe, but were not ſo by the latter; becauſe they did owe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and held in chiefe from the Crowne of France. So doth not the King of England from any forraine Prince or Potentate in the world. Yet upon examination, I found all this Supremacie too ſhort for our purpoſe, and too weak a foundation to beare all that building, which was raiſed upon it. For I am perſwaded, his Majeſtie out of his wiſdome will not deny, for all this, but that there is a greater and an higher Power within this Realme, than his owne ſingle. For there is a Power that can oblige the whole Kingdome by Laws, that can diſ-oblige them again from Laws, that can levie what taxes they ſhall think requiſite, that can take away the life, libertie, and eſtate of any man, by a Legiſlative Power, without any written Law. I am confident his Majeſtie is more juſt and wiſe, than to pretend of himſelfe alone to this Power and Supremacie, which is the high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt in England. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the argument from Supremacie, I did imagine as many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do, that Kings hold their authoritie immediately from God: But upon a review, I cannot find any one Text in all the Scripture that doth avouch it. Let me then entreat thee, if thou be any way ſcrupulous in this point, to lay aſide all prejudiciall conceits, and to examine the matter from the Originall ſincerely and impartially, no doubt but our good God, being duly called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will open thine eyes and heart, to underſtand the verie truth, which ſhall be my heartie prayer on thy behalfe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113480:3"/>
            <head>The Peoples Plea.</head>
            <head type="sub">To my reverend Brother, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Was troubled not a little, to heare that you are ſo much troubled with the Covenant, as that your taking thereof and leaving all your meanes are put in the ballance. Your particular doubts if they were knowne, might no doubt receive particular ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now at large, I conceive that as the publike difference of the State, ſo your private ſcruples may concerne, either the Eccleſiaſticall Government, or the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike power of king and Parliament. In the former, you are loth perhaps to vow the extirpation of the Prelacy; In the other, you may ſtick at preſerving the Rights of Parliament, and Liberties of Kingdome (which are your owne) with your eſtate and life; which as ſome interpret, is by a warre againſt the King that may ſeem unlawfull.</p>
            <p>To begin with the former, give me leave to aske, whither you do thinke our Hierarchy to be preſcribed by Gods Word, as alone neceſſarie for the Church; or only the beſt and moſt convenient, but that other formes of Church government be lawfull and allowable as well as that. If you conceive out late forme, abſolutely neceſſary and alone,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113480:4"/>1 You will finde it impoſſible to make good the whole frame of that Government, by any Scripture. Epiſcopacy it ſelfe, Dioceſan Epiſcopacy doth labour much in proving its Originall Title to be divine. And the reverend Biſhop who<note place="margin">Joſ. Nor. The Peace-maker, Sect. 6.</note> undertooke that proofe, doth now acknowledge this forme not to be eſſentiall to the being of a Church, though much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting the well or better being of it. As for Deanes, and Chapters, Archdeacons, Chancellours, Commiſſeries, &amp;c. much leſſe can they plead any warrant from Gods Word.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is too evident, that this government hath been verie much abuſed, by the pomp and pride, the avarice and ſloth of the Clergie, by their too neare complyancy with the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Church of Rome, by their medling too much in Civill and State aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ires, improper for their calling; but eſpecially, by the abominable corruption and fowle dealing of Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, Commiſſaries, Regiſters, Proctors, and Apparators in Eccleſiaſticall Courts. To ſay nothing of the Clergies depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon, and flatterng ſervice to the Kings Court, in rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Kings power to the prejudice of the Kingdome, as it is generally conceived.</p>
            <p n="3">3 By that opinion of the divinitie of our late Government, you muſt needs condemne all other Proteſtand Churches, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe which are beſt reformed, and moſt agreeing with us in Doctrine, for want of that Government and Diſcipline, which alone, you ſay God hath appointed in his Church. But I hope you will be adviſed better, then to entertaine ſuch a conceit, as may occaſion ſo great a breach between us and all the true Churches of God, as if we alone were to ſet up lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and go to heaven; other Nations, ſome for want of true Doctrine, others of Government and Diſcipline excluded all.</p>
            <p>But if you do allow of other formes of Government as no way croſſing, but agreeable to the Word of God, why ſhould it be any ſcruple of conſcience, in ſuch an indifferent caſe, to joyne with the maine body of this Kingdome, in pulling down the Prelacy as an old decayed houſe, which is no way neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, but hath been much abuſed and given great offence to many, yea conceived to be inconvenient for the ſafety of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113480:4"/>
Kingdome, and in ſetting up another forme, agreeable to Gods Word, more ſafe and pleaſing to the people of the Land, and more complying with the beſt of the Proteſtand Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad? for you may obſerve how ever you vow your beſt endeavour, to extirpate the Hierarchy which the better and more religious ſort of the whole Land, have much and long diſtaſted; yet you do not vow to ſet up any other particular forme, but onely in generall, the beſt according to the Word of God, and example of the beſt and Reformed Churches, Which me thinks everie good man ſhould deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of himſelfe, though no Covenant were propoſed, much more ſhould he joyn with his whole Countrey, going before him, and calling for his aſſiſtance</p>
            <p>Perhaps you may thinke (to come unto the other maine point) that there wanteth authority ſufficient in theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings; you may ſcruple at joyning in a Covenant, much more in Armes, and there to hazard your life and ſtate againſt the King, as it ſeemes to many. And here indeed, there will be ſome worke to perſwade you to a right underſtanding of things; ſo much hereto ſore has the Kings power been cried up, eſpecially by the Clergie, the choiceſt flowers of whoſe preferments did onely grow at Court, and the Parllament cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed downe as faſt, eſpecially by ſuch as were deſirous to prey upon the Kingdom without controule.</p>
            <p>Now then firſt I ſay, that neither the Covenant nor the Arms are taken againſt the King, but for him both. In the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant it is expreſt, To defend the Kings Majeſties perſon, and authoritie. And the Armes do ſpeake as much, being ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for the King and Parliament; however the king being miſ-adviſed by evill Councellours, do ſeeme in perſon to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare againſt them. But had there been any evill intention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Majeſtie, there might have been ſet up another Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie before this time: For my part, I am undoubtedly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, if he ſhould really and fully comply with his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he ſhould have as glorious a Government, but far more eaſie, contented &amp; ſweet, then hitherto he hath ever enjoyed. A Phyſitian giveth his Patient a potion that ſeemeth bitter,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113480:5"/>
and he is verie loth to take; and if the diſeaſe be unruly, he is bound too, without any evill will or meaning to wards him, but only for his health and good. Eares that have been long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the deſcanting muſicke of flatterie, will at firſt much diſtaſt the harſh and plaine notes of truth, though indeed more truly harmonious.</p>
            <p>I know verie well, there is no paſſing for me thus. It will be demanded, Who made the Parliament the Kings Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? Or how may any Subjects take up Armes, though not againſt his Perſon, yet againſt his will? Yes: If truth may be ſpoken without offence, whereunto the Statutes for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon heretofore gave ſmall freedome. The Parliament may be called the Kings Phyſitians, and may alſo take up Armes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in their owne defence, againſt his will, for his or the Kingdomes good.</p>
            <p>Take wee that common Axiom for the ground of all, that Rule eternall, as the Peace-maker <note n="*" place="margin">Sect. 22.</note> ſayes, which in a Kingdome, where tyranny prevaileth not, is unqueſtionable; <hi>Salus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli ſuprema Lex:</hi> The good and ſafetle of the people, and Kingdome, is the moſt fundamentall Law of all government. There cannot be well conceived any other aime or end, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore people ſhould chooſe them Kings, or any other forme of Rule, but only for their owne defence and well-fare; and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly not for the good of their Kings or Governours prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, but only in relation to their owne, and as it is involved in the common good of all. What Tyrants aimed at, who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced men under their ſubjection, as <hi>Nimrod</hi> and the like, it is no way materiall to ſpeak of, when we deale upon lawfull and juſt Governments, ſuch as our owne. A learned Doctor, <note n="*" place="margin">Dr. Fearne in Conſcience ſatisfied, Sect. 5.</note> pleading the Kings cauſe, though hee hath heaped many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours about the originall of Government, which as occaſion is offered, I ſhall diſcover, yet ſeemeth ingenuouſly to grant this Axiom, That the ſafetie of the Common-wealth is the higheſt end; and unto that end all other are meanes, and that the Higher Power ought to miniſter unto that end. And the Apoſtle <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note> doth plainly ſpeak as much, He is the Miniſter of God for thy good, that is, the good of the Subject, of the People.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113480:5"/>
The Miniſter of God he is called, becauſe of Gods generall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; the Miniſter of man alſo hee may be called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the particular, whereof St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Submit your ſelves unto all manner Ordinance of man.</hi> To ſay Kings are the ordinance of man <hi>ſubjectivè,</hi> or for the qualification of their power, may ſeeme rather a ſhift, than a credible expoſition or anſwer. It is not likely St. <hi>Peter</hi> did dreame of either.</p>
            <p>Now this being granted, that the well-fare of the People governed, is the originall and finall cauſe of all Government and Governours, even of Kings; ſee what building may be raiſed upon this foundation, what conſequences depend upon it in generall: and ſo we will deſcend to our owne particular.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it followeth hence, That the Kingdome is not ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the Kings uſe, benefit, or good; but the King is ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the Kingdomes uſe, as the chiefe and ſupreme ordinarie meanes, to precure the Peoples well-fare and ſafetie. For that millions of men, of the ſame mold and temper, ſhould be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the benefit of one, as it is moſt unnaturall and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, ſo doth it reliſh too much of the Tyrant and Slave.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If the Kingdome or Peoples ſafetie be the higheſt end, and the King only the chiefe ordinarie meanes provided for this end; as the end is more noble <note n="*" place="margin">Keckerm. Syſtem. Log. lib. 1. cap. 18. Canon. 5. de fine primario, ex Ariſtot. mag. mor. 1. 7.</note> and excellent, and to be preferred before the means, as they are meanes; ſo is the whole Kingdome ſuperiour to the King, and the King, though <hi>Singulis major, univerſis minor,</hi> Leſſe than all in generall, though greater and above all in particular. And therefore in caſe it were neceſſarie, either for the King alone, or the whole Kingdome to be deſtroyed, who will not think it more juſt and reaſonable, that one ſhould ſave all, being ordained for their ſafetie, rather than all ſhould periſh to ſave one? <hi>Thou art worth ten thouſand of us,</hi> ſay the people <note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 3.</note> to King <hi>David;</hi> but not worth thirteen hundred thouſand, <note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 24. 9.</note> for all that. It is true, the meanes materially may be better than the end: But I ſay as meanes, they are ſubordinate and inferiour. Now a King or Governour in his beſt notion is but a meane for the Subjects happineſſe. It was indeed our Saviours infinite, but volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie goodneſſe, that being in the forme of God, &amp;c. hee would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113480:6"/>
ſo far emptie and debaſe himſelfe, as to be the meane of mans ſalvation. Let us hold to humane, or naturall means. I know it is objected, the King is the Head and Higheſt, therefore no way inferiour. How the King is the Head and Supreme, is elſewhere declared. But a politike Head is much different from the naturall. This being taken off, the body dyes. Till that all government be taken away, the politike body dyes not. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Head bee higheſt in place, the Body is above it in dignitie, eſpecially becauſe it beares the Heart, the principall part by <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Philoſophy, Fountaine of Life, Mint of the Spirits, and prime Seat of the Soule.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if this were the condition of Government at the firſt inſtitution, it muſt be the condition of all juſt and lawfull Governments unto this day, the Rule being eternall of <hi>Salus Populi:</hi> and whereſoever there is any failing or defect herein, there is ſo great a declination to Tyranny, more or leſſe. And therefore it is moſt conſiderable how a Kingdome began, or what prerogatives and authoritie the King had allowed him from the beginning; if all be employed and referred to this maine end, all is well, and the Government good, otherwiſe it doth regenerate, and may be corrected, however it began.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the naturall end of Government needs not be ſet downe in a written convention or compact, as ſome <note n="*" place="margin">Conſc. ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, Sect. 3.</note> would have it; For beſide, that when Government began in moſt Nations, they had no writing at all: It is impoſſible to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine or conceive, that reaſonable creatures ſhould ſubmit themſelves to the rule and command of others, for no end, or any other end, beſide their owne good. This cannot then but be ſuppoſed in all Governments, though no ſuch convention appeare in writing.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, if this end be diſappointed, and they which have authoritie and power given them by the people, for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples good, impugne, croſſe, and hinder the ſame, by ſpoyling, oppreſſing, and deſtroying them, that power and authoritie ceaſeth <hi>ipſo facto;</hi> there needeth no reſuming of it, as ſome would have: For being given in relation to an end, that end failing, the meanes do fall of themſelves. Nor can it be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113480:6"/>
that any reaſonable creatures would give authoritie and power againſt themſelves, and to their owne hurt, or intended at firſt to continue the ſame to their owns deſtruction, which was given only for their defence and preſervation. It fares too often with States, as with the Horſe in the Fable,</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Non Equitem dorſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, non froe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um depulit ore.</hi>
               </l>
               <lg>
                  <l>He took the ſaddle for defence,</l>
                  <l>But hath been jaded ever ſince.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Men are not tyed to the ordinarie Law of Horſes, but if <hi>Belle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rophon</hi> will drive his <hi>Pegaſus</hi> up to Heaven an unnaturall courſe, <hi>Pegaſus</hi> may be bold to turne off his Rider upon the earth.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, the peoples ſafety being the end of all juſt Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if that ſhould be invaded by the Governours or Kings themſelves, whom they have truſted over them, ſome meanes muſt needs be allowed them, to preſerve and recover the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me. Otherwiſe mankind, may eaſily be fruſtrated by fraude or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, of the maine end, for the preſerving whereof, they ſubjected themſelves to Rulers, and that without all remedy: which as I conceive, ought not to be ſuppoſed. Now in ſuch Kingdomes or Governments, as have Parliaments, Diets, and ſuch full Aſſemblies of the States, theſe meanes of preſerving <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> are more plaine, eaſie, and expedite, then elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, becauſe ſuch generall Aſſemblies can both judge truly of ſuch wrongs, and breach of common Liberties, and readily provide remedies for the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both which are more ſlowly and hardly done, where ſuch publike Aſſemblies are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: and therefore they be much more ſubject to tyrannies and oppreſſions, then the others are. But whenſoever it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears unto the Kingdome or Bodie of the people clearly, that the Governours in ſtead of procuring their good and ſafety, do ſpoile and oppreſſe them, as the obligation of rule and and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection is preſently void, the end failing upon which it was grounded, ſo they have liberty to provide for their owne wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, either by reforming what was amiſſe, or by limiting and qualifying the Authority and Prerogitives of thoſe Rulers, or removing that Government, or thoſe evill Governours (in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113480:7"/>
caſe of extreame neceſſity) and placing others is more hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes for the publike good; In all which, they may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully make uſe of their owne Strength, Power, and Armes, or any other, as occaſion ſhall require. For that the chiefe end of all Government ought not to be fruſtrated and diſ-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. D. Fearne argues, <hi>becauſe elect Monarches did ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed Paternall Government, therefore they ſucceeded in the ſame right and condition free from coertion, and removalls as fathers were, and ſo meant under the names of fathers in the fift Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</hi> But how followes it, becauſe they followed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, therefore they did follow in the ſame condition every way. Fathers have a naturall obligation, and a naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſtrangers have not ſo, Fathers have no other Intereſt but their childrens good, ſtrangers have, no it is certaine that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Fathers had any juriſdiction and power of the ſword, or if ever they had, and grew tyrannous, its as certaine their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren might caſt off their Government, though not their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood. As for the fift Commandement it belongs no more to Kings then other Governours, yea, and Teachers, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and other Superiours, whereof none ſo unmovable as Parents.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, and laſt of all, That end muſt regulate <note n="*" place="margin">Reckerm. Syſtem. Log. lib. 1. cap. 18. Canon. 4. de fine ult. ex A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtot. Polit. 1: 6. &amp; de Caelo 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.74.</note> all the meanes ſo, as they may beſt conduce for the attaining of the ſame. The King then being but a meanes, his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and Power muſt be regulated accordingly, as the people ſhall think meeteſt for their owne ſafety; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in our State as the Kingdom or people have 1. Intruſted their King with the cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge of ſeeing the Lawes executed, and obeyed, which are provided for their ſafety: ſo they have given Authority to the Parliament, by a neerer truſt, both to deviſe and make new Lawes, abrogating the unuſefull, and declaring the doubtfull and obſcure, with the Kings conſent in all, who is the chiefe Miniſter in executing the ſame. 2 So likewiſe to viſit and correct all abuſes in the State, yea to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Kings owne proceedings whether he hath rightly diſcharged his great truſt, and to controule his actions in caſe they ſwerve or decline from the bias of the publike good: and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113480:7"/>
here is the Phyſick I ſpeak of. 3 Which controuling, if it be withſtood, and find ſtrong lets and oppoſition, they may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take up Armes without and againſt the Kings will, upon occaſion. Fourthly and laſtly, in caſe there ſhould fall a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the King and his Parliament, upon or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Premiſſes, it is the ſafeſt way for a ſubject both in conſcience and common wiſdome, to adhere unto the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p>I know you may doubt of, and queſtion all theſe four par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars according to thoſe principles of Divinity and State, which a great faction of your ſhire and ſome other places have ignorantly followed. I will therefore endeavour to make them all good, and clear ſeverally thus:</p>
            <p n="1">That the King is intruſted by the Realme with his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, doth appeare partly, becauſe from thence he hath his power: partly, becauſe he cannot receive his Authoritie or Power from anie other: and laſtly, becauſe the Kingdome hath received a Superiour Authoritie to examine and controule his proceedings.</p>
            <p>The firſt reaſon is, The King hath his Power from the Kingdome and therefore his Authoritie. I muſt crave leave to diſtinguiſh theſe termes, which commonly are confounded and obſcure this whole buſineſſe. Authoritie then, is a right or lawfulneſſe to command, and to challenge obedience; ſuch as all Governours and Magiſtrates have, more or leſſe. But Power is a lawfull ability to force obedience, if upon chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge and command it be denyed. Theſe are two different things, becauſe they may bee, and are many times ſeparated; One may have a juſt and lawfull right to command, that wants compulſive meanes for coertion. Others may have great ſtrength to force, commonly called power, that are deſtitute of authority to command: and power is that which in all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments bears the greateſt ſway; and therefore in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and elſwhere, it is taken concretively, for the Governours and Magiſtrates themſelves, which have power at command, to force obedience unto their commands. Now there is no doubt, but the King hath full authority to command
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113480:8"/>
according to law, all ſuch as by law are ſubject into him. But if upon his commands obedience be denyed, whence I pray, hath he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a lawfull ability to force it? whence hath he power to make his authority good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but from the people? of himſelf he cannot have it, being but one man, not having the ſtrength of anie more; whereas this ability doth require the ſtrength of many. <hi>Vis unita fortior, vis om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ium unita fortiſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> many hands are abler then one; but the hands of all, ableſt of all. To keep a ſtrong guard for this purpoſe, eſpecially of ſtrangers, Ariſtotle and all that write of Politie will tell you, that it is the propertie of Tyrants; nor is ſuch ability <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> but <hi>Vis,</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence not power, becauſe unlawfull. And to keep an Army on foot continually, under other pretences thereby to affright and force his ſubjects, is little better: Therefore the Kings power muſt needs come from his owne peoples hands, and ſtrength, and from the ſame people muſt needs come his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie therefore. If any other ſhould give him authoritie, that were not able to make it good by power, it were given him but in vaine; nor were the people bound to make that good, which themſelves give not. Whence he hath his power then, from thence he muſt needs receive his authority alſo, even from the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed can hee receive it from any other. I heare ſome ſpeak, and preach, and write alſo, but ſee no proofe, that Kings have their authoritie and power immediately from God. And ſure, if they could fetch downe fire from Heaven, as <hi>Elias</hi> did, or ſtrike men dead with the breath of their mouths, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> did, for diſobedience; I ſhould grant their power deſcended immediately from Heaven. But wee neither ſee, nor heare of any ſuch miracles wrought by Kings. No power then imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from God, and therefore no authoritie, otherwiſe than all other Magiſtrates have. For as by Gods wiſdom <hi>Kings do raigne, and Princes decree juſtice, Prov.</hi> 8. 15. Even ſo by the ſame, <hi>do the Nobles rule, and all the Judges of the earth,</hi> ver. 16. And <hi>Rom. 13. 1. There is no Power but of God,</hi> that is, as it is expounded in the ſame place, not only ordained, but ordred by God, <hi>ſecundùm ſub &amp; ſupra,</hi> in ſeverall ranks, higher &amp; lower.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113480:8"/>
Kings then have their power from God no more than inferior<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Governours, <hi>Caeſar</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 19. 11.</note> no more than <hi>Pilate.</hi> So far as God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth of, and hath ordained all Societies of mankind, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments and Governours, both high and low, ſo far all au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and all power that is employed in diſcharging and maintaining the ſame, is in generall from God; but imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately from the People, executing the Ordinance of God. And therefore S. <hi>Peter, Eph.</hi> 2. 13. ſayes plainly thus, Everie Governour, both high and low, ſupreme and ſubordinate, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an humane ordination, or creature. Now then to anſwer as the Doctor does, that this is taken ſubjectively, in regard of the power it ſelfe, which is from God cauſally, and placed in man as the ſubject, or els to be underſtood of the qualifications, and ſeverall waies of executing that power in ſeverall termes of Government. Theſe may ſeem rather ſhifts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then ſolutions or expoſitions, the former being ſtrained againſt the former meaning of the words; the latter ſuch as (it is not likely) S. <hi>Peter</hi> ever dreamt of, being both againſt the ſtraine of Interpreters. For were it ſo that God immediately gave unto Kings their ruling power; Firſt, no other forme of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were lawfull, ſo that Ariſtocracies, and Democracies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humane inventions, as Dr. <hi>Feanne</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Conſc. ſatif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, Sect 3.</note> ſayes, would have no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> warrant from God for their proceedings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and for want of ſuch divine authoritie and power, as many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elons as they exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, ſo many murthers they committed; and as many fines or mulcts as they levied, ſo many robberies. Mee thinks our neighbours, the States of Holland, the Swiſſers, Griſons, and free Cities of Germany, ſhould not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> roliſh well this new do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Secondly, if Royall Authoritie came altogether from Heaven, it ſhould by right be the verie ſame upon all the earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But we find it far otherwiſe; no two States in the world al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing their Princes the verie ſame authoritie, in all points. In ſome things (perhaps) the Spanyard hath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> more than the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Engliſh, in ſome others the Engliſh more than he, the French more than both, the Dane, Swede, Polander<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Scottiſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> leſſe than any of them. The Turk, Chinoys, and other ſuch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> abſolute Princes, more than all theſe. Yet all Kings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Do ſome (I pray) take leſſe authoritie than God allowes them, or do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113480:9"/>
take more? How may it be knowne, how far Gods al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance goes? No Scripture doth reſolve it. And I preſume, there came no Angell from Heaven to order it. Theſe limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and qualifications of power, Dr. <hi>Fearne</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Conſc. ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, Sect. 3.</note> ſayes, are meer inventions of men. But is it lawfull for men to limit, or quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that, which God himſelfe hath otherwiſe, and more fully ordred? Certainly, if this be unlawfull, as it cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if God himſelfe be the immediate Author of Royall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, then all the Realmes in Chriſtendome do verie much offend. For in all, the abſolute power of Kings is limited, though in all diverſly. This is acknowledged to proceed from the People, as correcting Gods Ordinance, which without all doubt, is not in any Peoples power to do. And therefore all Kings may take upon them, nay ought indeed to take upon them, an abſolute and arbitrarie power, nor is it any treaſon to perſwade them therunto, if that be from God, and theſe limia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; qualifications, meere inventions of men. I know not whither wee ſhall run anon, by following this new doctrine. Yet ſome where I have ſeen thirteene, I cannot ſay, proofs, (they were ſo weak) but offers, to make good the immed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> Commiſſion of Kings from heaven; all ſo ſhort and wide from the mark, that I ſhould wrong the Reader to repeat them. For either in generall they ſhow, that Kings &amp; all Goveronrs indeed are authorized by Gods generall Ordinance, &amp; the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of them aſſigned by God his eſpeciall providence, or els they concern <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Kings of the Iſraelites, which doth no way concerne other Kings: when I heare ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe teſtimonie for others, as I read <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 15. for thoſe Kings, <hi>Thou ſhalt make him King over thee whom the Lord thy God ſhall chooſe,</hi> it will be credible to me, that God hath an immediate hand, if not in their authority, yet in their perſonall aſſignement: And till we have ſome more likely proofe then hitherto I have ſeen, give us leave to ſuppoſe ſtill, that thoſe men who have limited the authority of Kings (by their owne confeſſion) did firſt give the ſame. I find no proofe at all, that ſuch authoritie comes from God: till then I may well ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that thoſe men who have limited the authoritie of Kings, did at firſt give it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113480:9"/>Laſt of all, if the King were not entruſted with his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, by the Kingdom, how could the Kingdom have Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to examine and controll his proceedings, in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thereof? But this Authority they have, and do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> therewith; as now I am to prove upon the ſecond point; upon which the former point will neceſſarily follow.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath full Authority from the Realm, to examine the Kings proceedings, and to controll them if irregular, that is, either treſpaſſing againſt the known Laws, or otherwiſe encroaching upon the Subjects liberty and ſafety, common experience, and the continuall practiſe of <hi>Parliaments</hi> doth make it evident. Indeed his Perſon they do not ſtrike at, and to blemiſh his dignity and honour, they do ſpare all that may be, in the eyes of Subjects and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; that he may ſtill retain his full glory and luſtre, both at home and abroad. And it is preſum'd, that he does nothing perſonally, and therefore nothing againſt the Laws, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Miniſters and Agents. But all his unlawfull acts by ſuch Miniſters, they do reverſe, and puniſh the Inſtruments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, though immediately commanded by the King. Now this they can no otherwiſe do, but as they are authorized by the Kingdom; whereof the Noblemen are a part themſelves, the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> choſen by the Commons of the Land. Nor indeed can they well have any other abuſes to reform, but ſuch as the King either commands, or approveth, and connives at. For all others commonly, are redreſſed by the King, and ordinary Courts of Juſtice. But ſuch enormities, as grow at Court, either by command, or toleration and connivence, the <hi>Parliament</hi> onely can redreſſe. And therefore have Courtiers ſo much poſſeſt His Majeſty againſt <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> as if they did eclipſe his Glory, becauſe they may not themſelves grate upon the Subjects, and play <hi>Rex</hi> quietly, without queſtion and cenſure of <hi>Parliament.</hi> Dr <hi>Ferne,</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Conſ. ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. Sect. 4.</note> ſeems to allow the <hi>Parliament</hi> no Authority, but onely an aſſentin making Laws with His Majeſtie. But this power of viſiting the publick abuſes, both in Court and Kingdom, is every
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113480:10"/>
whit as great, and as neceſſary a Power, for maintaining of <hi>Salus Populi.</hi> And beſide the command of the Subjects purſes, in granting of Subſidies, which onely belongs to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> is a great and very conſiderable Authority. As for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Laws, if weele ſpeak properly, the King doth rather aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to them, who bring the Acts ready penn'd and Voted, then they to him. Certainly a great providence and bleſſing of God it is, that we have the benefit of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> to purge out ſuch corruptions, as will daily grow, in ſo great a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick body. Otherwiſe, in a few yeers (as by dear experience we have lately found) by the flattery, and craft of miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous wits, working for their own covetous and evill ends, the liberty of the Subject, and the ſafety of the Realm, would be quickly undermined and overthrown.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, But if the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould be withſtood, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd; if oppoſition made to hinder them, in reforming the abuſes of Court and Countrey, and providing due means for the ſafety of the people, (which was my third point) muſt they ſit ſtill then, and quietly ſuffer ſuch abuſes as they can not reform? And ſhall the ſafety of the State ſuffer, through their weakneſſe and diſability? No doubt but <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> the welfare of the Realm, which is the chief end of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ought to be better provided for, then ſo. If ſuch obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles come in their way, as can not be removed by ordinarie means, no doubt but the Kingdom is to allow them power, to make the Authority good, where with they have entruſted them, and to preſerve their own ſafety. Otherwiſe the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is all in vain, becauſe every oppoſition and diſobedience may hinder the execution and diſcharge thereof; and ſo the publick weal may ſuffer without all remedy. As Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy ſaies, <hi>Fruſtra eſt potentia, que nunquam reducitur in actum:</hi> Such a natural faculty is in vain, which cannot be actuated; ſo is that Authoritie in a State, which every diſturbance may fruſtrate and diſappoint. Now as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſayes of God and Nature, ſo it is to be preſumed of a Kingdom, that it doth nothing in vain; and therefore, that together with Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, it gives power alſo (having all the power in its own
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113480:10"/>
hands) to enable the diſcharge thereof. This power can be no other then <hi>Poſſe Regni,</hi> the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdom; <hi>Quid enim contra vim, ſine vi fieri poteſt.</hi> Forcible oppoſition muſt have forcible reſiſtance. This <hi>Poſſe Regni</hi> then in caſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, the <hi>Parliament</hi> may, and ought, to raiſe and employ, even without the King, if he do croſſe himſelf, or joyn with ſuch as diſturbe them in their proceedings.</p>
            <p>I know here comes in a great out-cry, againſt Rebellion; as if it could be no leſſe, for any to take up Arms, without, or againſt the Kings will. And true it is in ſome ſence. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the right thereof, and then judge. For private men, of their own heads; nay more, for Magiſtrates, Officers, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, be they never ſo many, never ſo great, which derive their Authoritie from the King, and therefore in reſpect of him are as private men, to raiſe a War by their own Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, without him, much more againſt him is legall Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. But the <hi>Parliament</hi> derives their Authoritie, not from the King, though he be entruſted with aſſembling and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving them: no more then a Trumpeter gives authority to fight, when he gives the Signall. But all their Authoritie doth come from the Kingdom; whereof one part is preſent perſonally, the Nobles, and the other part by their choice Atturneys. And all theſe, have ſo much a neerer truſt from the Kingdom, then the King himſelf, as all their private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, are more concentrick to <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> the publick good. For the King hath a proper center of his own to move about; he hath private ends, and different Intereſts from the people, for his Prerogatives, and Family. In regard whereof, though he hath a very great truſt, yet may they not in any diſcretion, give him ſo neer a truſt, as to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Parliament</hi> taking up Arms, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorizing others, for their own defence, being threatned, hindered, and diſturbed in their proceedings, and <hi>Salus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli,</hi> the common Liberty not yet ſecur'd, which had lately been ſo much wrong'd, they are no waies liable to the charge of Rebellion, nor any that joyn with them to vindicate the Kingdoms Intereſt; but thoſe rather, who preſume to turn
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113480:11"/>
the Arms of the Kingdom againſt it ſelf, and againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for diſcharging faithfully and zealouſly that truſt, which the Kingdom hath repoſed in them. Now againſt the former, private men, and others of Authority, that hold from the King, the Scriptures, which are alledged common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. and other places, may have place; and the Statutes of the Realm alſo. But againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> who themſelves are of thoſe higher powers, whereof St <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, no Scripture doth ſpeak, nor hath any Statute force.</p>
            <p>You may demand perhaps, why the <hi>Parliament</hi> never took up Arms before, if it be a thing ſo lawfull. Tis true. Though in behalfs of <hi>Parliaments</hi> much blood hath been ſhed in this Land, yet hath it not been uſuall for the <hi>Parliaments</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to manage a War, becauſe it hath been hitherto in ſome ſort impoſſible. For the Kings having the truſt of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and diſſolving, have ever uſed, to call ſlowly, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ſpeedily, upon the leaſt offer of diſtaſte. I remember an old ryme to this purpoſe, Much complain'd of, little amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Subſidies granted, <hi>Parliament</hi> ended: ſo that many of the common ſort beleeved, there was no other uſe of, nor buſines for a <hi>Parliament,</hi> but to grant Subſidies. No thinking for them of a War, that were ſo uncertain of their own continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Now theſe preſent Arms were begotten by Neceſſity, and brought forth by Opportunity. The <hi>Parliament</hi> intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a through-reformation, and corruptions being grown to a great head, through ſo many nullities, and ſo long diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> they were not able to compaſſe their intents, without the diſcontents of many. For to redreſſe publick Inconveniences, it could not be, but many perſonall miſchiefs muſt be endured in private. This bred great ſtore of Malignants; and they threatned great ſtormes of danger to the Reformers: At laſt, the King himſelf was drawn away, with intent to diſturb all by Arms; as did appear by the L: <hi>Digbies</hi> Letter, by the Kings guard (as ſome * call it) raiſed at <hi>Ysrk,</hi> and other diſcoveries. Now unleſſe the <hi>Parliament,</hi> would ſuffer the wheel to carry all back again with violence,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113480:11"/>
which they had done, and expoſe themſelves and heirs to utter ruine, for their good ſervice, they muſt needs defend themſelves and their proceedings, and ſecure their own and their Countreys ſafetie, with the Arms and power of the Countrey which had entruſted them. Yet had they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken this all in vain, if Gods providence, and their own wiſedom, had not extraordinarily provided them an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. For if things had ſtood as heretofore, the King might have ſuddenly diſſolved the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and expoſed them all, to the fury of diſcontented Malignants. But they ſeeing at firſt, what a <hi>Hydra</hi> of corruptions they were to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter withall, in a through-reformation, obtained of His Majeſtie an Act, for continuation of this Sitting, untill they had finiſhed all their deſignes. Having this aſſurance, they reſolved to venture the hazard of a War, rather then to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their own, and the Kingdoms ſafety. 'Twas not their deſire, but fear; Being unwilling and forc't thereunto, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the goodneſſe of their Cauſe, God hath proſpered their endeavours, and judged on their ſide. And it may be well hoped, this ſhort War, will occaſion a long and a happy Peace. It is the travail of our Kingdom, for the time pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. But when the Man-childe is born into the world, and the thorough-reformation perfected, no doubt, but there will be much and laſting joy over the whole Land, for the ſhort ſorrow that it hath endured.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Now to come unto that which was propoſed in the laſt place; In ſuch a difference betweene the King and Parliament, as now is fallen, that it is ſafer to truſt our ſelves on the Parliaments ſide, both in conſcience and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, thus it may appeare. 1. Though it were doubtfull or obſcure, on which ſide the juſtice of this Cauſe did ſtand; yet let us conſider, that the higheſt point of Supreame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in this Kingdom doth conſiſt in repealing and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Lawes. As for executing them after they are made, with other circumſtances of government, calling Aſſemblies,<note n="*" place="margin">Dr Fearne Conſ ſatisfied. Sect. 4.</note> Treating with forreine Princes, ſending Embaſſies, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing officers of ſtate, and Judges of Courts &amp;c. In all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113480:12"/>
which the Parliament alſo may interpoſe, if they ſinde it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for the common ſafety, theſe are but ſmall matters in compariſon of enacting obligatory Lawes. This higheſt and Supreame authority of the Realme, is placed in a full Parliament; though for the execution of Laws, and ordinary Adminiſtration, the ſupremacy be in the King alone and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in relation to the Pope, to forreign Princes and States as the oath of Supremacy and Alleagiance doe declare. And this full Parliament doth conſiſt of three parts, the King, the Peeres, and the Houſe of Commons. But they muſt all agree, and goe together. Neither the King and Commons without the Nobility, nor yet the King and Nobles without the Commons can doe it. Now in ſuch equall and coordinate powers, if upon a difference one ſhould ſtand againſt two, is it not ſafter in Conſcience for a ſubject, to joyne with two of them againſt one, then with one againſt two? eſpecially to joyne with thoſe two, which have the neereſt truſt, of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our liberty &amp; ſafety recommended to them? Secondly, The Parliaments cauſe, doth cleerly appeare to be more ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyable. For all their proceedings have been warrantable, as by the firſt ground of all government, in maintayning <hi>populi ſalutem,</hi> the publicke good, ſo according to the ſetled conſtitution of this kingdome, in reforming grand enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and when they could not otherwiſe ſecure themſelves or the kingdome; in taking the power of the kingdome, which had entruſted and authorized them, to make their Acts good againſt Delinquents and Malignants; &amp; all ſuch as went about to reverſe or diſturbe their proceedings, and deſtroy their perſons. On the other ſide, the King deſerted them, purpoſely, to joyne with ſuch Delinquents and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants, in armes againſt them, to hinder them, and in them the publike good. What then can there be ſafer for a mans conſcience to reſt upon, then the goodneſſe of a cauſe in ſuch a maine difference? The Parliament did but their duties; and for doing that, were in danger of utter undoing. The King voluntarily forſooke them, with intention (as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd) to have deſtroyed them, had He prevailed. Was it
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113480:12"/>
not juſt then for them to defend themſelves, with the power of that kingdome, in whoſe cauſe and ſervice they were like to ſuffer? Laſtly, in ordinary wiſdome, is it not fitter for one of us, ordinary ſubjects, to adhere unto thoſe, who maintaine our Intereſts and liberty, &amp; of whoſe Aſſemblies our children may be members; then to venture our lives and fortunes for the Prerogative, wherein neither we, nor our children have any hope of Intereſt, but is rather prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, and to the great diſadvantage of us and ours, as it hath been managed? Nay more; for us to deſert the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by neutrality, who doe hazard their lives and eſtates for us and our good, without any private hope or end of their owne; much more to appeare againſt them, to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of our owne lives and fortunes, can it be any thing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then foule unthankefulneſſe, and extreme folly? By this time, I hope, Sir, you have receiv'd ſo much content and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, to the principall doubts, that petty ſcruples ſhall not worke upon you ſo far, as to make you liable to thoſe two illiberall vices. Tis true. They are not many yeares, ſince you left the Univerſity, where young wits, doe uſe to dreame of nothing but Biſhopricks and Archbyſhopricks. But you are become a man and put away childiſhneſſe; you are ſetled in a place, where to do God, his Church, and your Country ſervice. I know your meekeneſſe and ingenuity, is far from their ambitious humour, who relliſh nothing, but Dignities in the Church, and Court preferments: contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the meane ruſticity of countrey miniſters. I pray let theſe men themſelves enjoy their humour. Doe you but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low your owne quiet and milde temper, I doubt not, but what I have written may prevaile, though for want of time and bookes not written with that diligence, as the weight of the matter did require. Let me intreate you, ſeriouſly to conſider of theſe things; And the All-wiſe God give you a right underſtanding in them all.</p>
            <closer>So prayeth,
<signed>Yours, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
